If you are running something like AWS
Lambda or any managed service and you
want to provide telemetry data of that
service, how do you do that? You either
provide it in 20 formats like DataDog,
New Relic, Dash Zero, or you have a
standardized format that everybody can
understand. And OpenTelemetry actually
was the first approach to standardize
this format, right? So that you have no
proprietary data. If you look at a lot
of vendors, they say we support
OpenTelemetry. What that means is that
you can send them OpenTelemetry data.
They take that data and convert it into
their internal format. What we have
built is something where the data is
always OpenTelemetry because all the
models by default understand the format,
understand OpenTelemetry, and therefore
can really work with it similar to what
they can do with code, right?
>> [music]
>> Just to dig in, start by giving us a bit
of context of like Dash Zero, the
company you've built and are running
today. Tell us a few words about it and
and some of its core. Yeah, so um we are
an AI-native observability platform.
When we started, we were not
promoting AI-native. At the beginning,
we were OpenTelemetry-native.
And that turned out to be a good
foundation for AI, by the way. So the
idea was there's a new standard in
observability called OpenTelemetry,
which standardizes the format of the
telemetry data, logs, metric, traces,
end user events,
and also standardizes the tagging system
on that telemetry data, which is called
the semantic convention. So
post name now is host underscore name or
host.name. And um that that is the way
we have started. So we built a full
platform for logs, traces, metric, end
user monitoring,
taking only OpenTelemetry data into it
and keeping it as OpenTelemetry and
making the the out of the semantic
convention by creating context. So, if
you look at a trace, you see all the
logs, you see the metrics, the
underlying infrastructure, everything in
context based on the semantic
convention. And we try to make a very
easy onboarding flow, PLG type of
sales motion, and and having it
easy to use. So, let's start by why why
I think it's also meaningful, right?
Before OTel,
it is every vendor, including myself as
Instana, did their own format, right?
So, we had an agent, and so you
specified your own format, and you send
your own format.
>> old-school agent. This is the tracing
agent, not an AI agent. Exactly. That's
the old-school agent that you install on
your host, basically, and that captures
the data, right? The CPU utilization,
the logs, and and the traces. Exactly,
it's not an AI agent. The benefit was
that you could make everything you
needed for your platform, right? Into
the format, and you could do do some
auto metrics. So, for example, if the
agent was running on the host, you could
add the host name because you were
running on it, and just send it over,
right?
Um and Open Telemetry actually was the
first approach to standardize
this um this format, right? So, that you
have no proprietary data. And the And I
think the main drivers were the cloud
providers
because if you are running something
like AWS Lambda or any managed service,
and you were to provide
telemetry data of that service, how do
you do that, right? You either provide
it in 20 formats like Data Dog, New
Relic, Datadog,
or you have a standardized format that
everybody can understand. And that's how
it started, right? So, I would also say,
if you look at a lot of vendors, they
say, "We We support Open Telemetry."
What that means is that you can send
them Open Telemetry data, but I would
say still 90% of the vendors, they take
that data and convert it into their
internal format. Right.
>> Because that's how the platform is
built. So, you can send it, but then in
the system essentially the tagging
system etc. is gone, right? Because it's
now
datadog format or Yeah. format of any
other vendor, right? And I think
what we have built is something where it
the data is always open telemetry. It
stays open telemetry. I think there's
only one tag that is mandatory
and that's service name.
Okay. So, the only
>> tag the the only tag in and and so
essentially everything that emits
telemetry data is a service, right? In
that that sense. And so, if you have a
service, I don't know, payment service
and you send a log, you add the
service.name equals payment service.
Yeah. And if you have a metric of that,
you do the same and now you can
correlate everything on a service level
by saying give me all the metrics, logs,
traces Right. of that service name.
Yeah, that's that's the only thing
that's mandatory and that's also that's
also a bit of a problem, I would say,
for vendors because we also see that a
lot of the data we get from customers at
the beginning does not have all the
information that would be needed. For
example, if you now ask, "Give me all
the logs of that pod or that host."
If that log does not have the pod name
and the host name as a tag, we can't do
it, right? Because
again, going back to proprietary agents,
there we could add that information to
the
log or Yeah. ourselves. But now we are
relying on the customer sending us the
right context and if we don't get that
context, we can't
really
Yeah. recreate it, right? By the way, I
think there is also a big chance for AI.
When these LLMs came out and we started
experimenting with it, that we saw that
we get really good results with those
platforms like Claude, for example. We
use Claude internally giving us really
good results by saying, "Hey, analyze
this trace, right?" And be
>> Right. put in the trace, which is
literally a text format of tags, right?
>> Yeah. Which is specified by
OpenTelemetry. And now the thing is,
because it is actually open source, it's
openly documented, it's an open
standard, all these models are trained
on the data, and they literally
understand that host.name is a host
name, and they can start basically
understanding the context, getting what
is
uh HTTP status code 404.
Yeah.
>> know that it's actually a problem,
right? And now it can really analyze
these things. So, OpenTelemetry turned
out to be really useful because all the
models by default understand the format,
understand OpenTelemetry, and therefore
can really
work with it, similar to what they can
do with code, right? Right.
>> It's like it's a text structure, text
format, very well specified. It has a
syntax, it has semantics, and so it it
can actually really do interesting
things and analyze uh
uh telemetry data. Uh
I mean, we were really impressed by the
output, right? And by the way, funny
story is when we started, there is a
OpenTelemetry sample application, also
open source. Yeah.
>> And the sample application has very well
documented problems in it, right?
Different types of errors. And when we
started with LLMs, we asked the LLMs
about problems in that sample
application because it was running, and
it always gave us perfect answers.
And we were super excited at the
beginning, but it turned out the LLM was
also trained with the problems
documented
>> Yeah. on the actual list. So, it could
do it because it was
>> cheat the test. It could cheat the test
because it knew the problems up front,
right? So, so results were the amazing
at the beginning, but then we figured
out, "Okay, it's actually not that
amazing with other things." And then we
kind of connected the dots that it was
already trained on the documentation of
the problems, right? So, um That's
interesting.
drilling into that a little bit so like
the the LLM's were naturally better and
all that was like a nice a nice
kind of
benefit of choosing open technologies
that the LLM's came pre-made or
pre-ready
to to process open telemetry data. Is it
they're not very good at analyzing
traces, they're not very good at like
understanding time series data, they
don't
you know the the volume of data a little
bit is there. I guess it
On those fronts like hotel note hotel
like that doesn't terribly matter,
right? Or like I guess what has been
your experience in terms of like the the
native support of like just drop this
trace in
into whatever Claude or
ChatGPT and and get some result.
I think there are two separate problems,
right? One is you have one trace and
there is a problem in it, right? And the
erroneous fan or something. If you do if
you do drop that trace into for example
Claude, I think it will definitely come
up with an analysis say hey, I see
there's a problem with this trace and
depending on the metadata it gets, for
example it's a database problem and it
gets gets a database status code in
there from an Oracle database, it will
look up that
error code and will give you context on
that error. So they are really good at
saying hey, this is actually I don't
know exhaustion of the connection pool
in the Oracle database and you should do
this and that based on the
documentation. This is essentially what
you would do as a human, right? You you
would see that code and then search for
it and it does the job for you. Where it
is not really good if you have thousands
or millions of traces to figure out
anomalies instead of A because the they
they can't really do that large amount
of data, right? The volume. So what you
have to do there is you have to provide
the AI agent the right tools
to do the analysis, right? So have a
functionality, for example, called
triage. What triage does it it compares
you give it a million
traces and ask is there any anomaly in
it for erroneous traces and it would
look at all the
um tags and would tell you, "Oh, the the
the ones with the error always have this
customer ID
as uh uh
as as a tag and then it will return that
result." And now we provide that tool to
the agent
through an MCP server, right? And the
agent can now the agent can now use that
tool that triage tool right and it will
use it, right? Autonomously it will say,
"Okay, there's a problem. Let's figure
out if there are any anomalies, so let's
use that triage feature." So, yes, you
have to build
your API essentially in a way that it
works for the agent and that the agent
can use it. Yeah, to be consumed. So, I
think maybe let's delineate. So, we want
to talk a little bit about sort of
the the the way in which AI meets uh you
know, observability uh needs and sort of
that type of analysis. And I think there
are sort of three uh uh pillars here to
to talk about. One is, you know, what we
started talking about here, which is
more the kind of AI powered, like how do
you how do you use AI to an agent to to
to be smarter, right? To sort of you
know, offload more of that work, provide
good functionality. The second is about
agent as a consumer uh and you know, I
think it started now talking about the
agent will consume So, I want to
disabiguate a little bit of uh which
agent is that? Is it your agent or is it
like class agent? And then maybe we go a
little bit more philosophical, talk
about sort of product and talk about
scope and uh
uh and the likes. Um so, maybe maybe
let's start so we started, you know,
like digging a lot more like the agents
can do this, it can't do that. Uh so,
why don't we talk like you have a bunch
of agent powered observability. Um I
don't know how you call them, I'll let
you say that in a second, but under the
under the mantle of agent zero uh is the
capabilities.
So tell us about that. Like what are
what is what are useful things to do
today with AI when it comes to to this
world? I mean there's when we started
agent zero was just one AI agent but
then over time we figured out that there
are actually a lot of use cases where
where I agents make sense and now agent
zero is just a platform for agents and
we have different ones and I think the
most prominent in the whole space
there's also a category AI SRE agents
Yeah. is essentially troubleshooting,
right? I mean you you get a call 3:00
a.m. in the morning there's an outage
you have a problem and now you want AI
to support you in figuring out what the
problem is.
>> [music]